Guide to the Joel E. Spingarn Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Joel E. Spingarn Collection
1910-1947
JWJ MSS 11
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.4
(1 box)
The Joel Spingarn Collection contains Correspondence with various persons, including W. E. B. Du Bois, and a German translation of a James Weldon Johnson poem done by Spingarn's wife, Amy.
Spingarn, Joel Elias, 1875-1939
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Joel Spingarn Collection contains items presented to the James Weldon Johnson Collection, most likely by Amy Spingarn, Mr. Spingarn's widow, after his death in 1939.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
JOEL E. SPINGARN (1875-1939)
Joel Spingarn was an educator and writer who published works on literary criticism and collections of his own poetry. He is most well-known for his involvement in social reform, primarily his work with the NAACP and his establishment of the Spingarn Medal, given to recognize the contributions of African-Americans.
Scope and Contents
This finding aid was produced from a previously existing manuscripts inventory. All pertinent information has been retained.
African American authors -- 20th Century -- Archives; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Du Bois, W. E. B. (William Edward Burghardt), 1868-1963; Spingarn, Amy Einstein, 1883-1980; Spingarn, Joel Elias, 1875-1939
- Correspondence, 1926; Series I
  - Braithwaite, William S., 1926 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    To: 3 / From: 0
  - Brawley, Benjamin, 1917-32 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Includes letter to Mrs. JES To: 6 / From: 0
  - Carver, George Washington, 1923 Sep 19 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    To: 1 / From: 0
    Includes letter from Walter White, forwarding letter to JES, 1923 Sep 20
  - Cecchi, Emilio, 1938 Feb 16 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Cook, George William, 1917-19 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    To: 6 / From: 0
  - Davis, Harry E., 1931 Apr 22 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - DeSuze, Carl, 1935 Sep 22 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Dorsey, Emmett, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Douglas, Aaron, 1928 Jul 19 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - DuBois, William E. B., 1910-38 (Box 1, Folder 10-12)
    To: 86 / From: 1
    Includes one letter from DuBois to James Weldon Johnson
  - Gregory, Montgomery, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Harrison, Richard B., 1931-33 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Letters to Mrs. JES
    To: 4 / From: 0
  - Hughes, Langston, 1930-34 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Hunt, H. A., 1934 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Hunton, Addie W., 1918 Feb 14 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Johnson, Hall, 1933 Mar 17 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Letter to Miss Spingarn
  - Johnson, James Weldon, 1920, 1929, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Includes 2 letters to Mrs. JES
    To: 7 / From: 0
  - Johnson, J. Rosamond, 1927 Mar 15 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Logan, Rayford W., 1938 Jan 4 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Nash, Roy, 1917 May 7 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Randolph, Richetta G., 1934 Jul 6 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Reid, Ira De A., 1938 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    To: 2 / From: 0
  - Russell, Charles Edward, 1932 Jul 6 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Van Vechten, Carl, 1947 Nov (Box 1, Folder 26)
    (letter from Mrs. JES)
    To: 0 / From: 1
  - Weaver, Archie L., 1931 May 25 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - White, Walter
    Related Archival Materials note
    See: George Washington Carver, Box 1, folder 3
  - Wilson, Edward N., 1937 Mar 5 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Young, Charles, 1917 Jun 10 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    letter from Young to Frank M. Liston
    1 letter
- Miscellany, n.d.; Series II
  - Translation into German of James Weldon Johnson's "Go Down Death" by Mrs. JES (Amy Spingarn), typescript (Box 1, Folder 29a)
    [Clippings re: Mrs. JES and Spingarn Medal pamphlet formerly found here removed to clippings file 11/77]